So today's lecture is going to be about
planning and multi-step reasoning. Um so
today's lecture we are going to cover
three papers on multi-step reasoning and
planning let's start with this paper um
from
uh ICML of last year. So the title uh of
the paper is language agent tree
research unifies reasoning acting and
planning in uh language models. So the
kind of the target the types of
applications that we want to target in
multi-step task are tasks that we uh
need not only need to reason about
things but also need to act through
those reasoning steps and um kind of
search our trajectories or optimize
trajectories on how we get to a final
correct answer. So in the reasoning
step, the model needs to think about
what needs to be done. For example, what
the budget is, where where the plan is.
This these are the reasoning steps for a
trip or vacation planning prompt. The
act is okay. Now that you have
certain types of reasoning or thinking,
how do you kind of gather more
information or act on these reasoning
steps? For example, the action could be
a browsing uh browsing the web,
generating a query to search uh readits
Reddit or a travel blog and so so on.
And then another step is search um
given these feedback or the information
that's uh gathered online um how can we
refine our uh our plan so far? Maybe we
can consider alternative destinations
uh search new things to do while we are
there and so on. So there were a a
series of reasoning action and search
steps that needs to be done to solve
this problem of for example planning a
trip. So the problem um or the challenge
that this paper specifically wanted to
address was the following. Um
the goal here was let's go from the LLM
generate a plan and like executing on on
that plan to really try to encourage
diversification and exploration of
different types of uh plans or path that
the model can take. uh because models
and this is true still to this day that
they can be
weak in creating a diversity of
solutions or acting upon them and um
planning multiple steps of optimization
to reach a solution. Um so this paper
focused on bringing known techniques
from reinforcement learning and multi-
kind of multi-step planning that existed
in the past um including multi-step uh
Monte Carlo research into the LLM
reasoning path. Um and given that the
models can uh take feedback in it also
introduce ways for the model to take
different feedback as the model explores
with the the environment and bring that
back in in order to f refine and
optimize future uh plans and search
processes.
So
just a quick kind of example of how uh
how this worked. Uh for example the the
prompt is to plan a trip to Hawaii.
There are different ways and different
actions that the model can take. Um so
it can for example the if we sample the
model for this prompt the model might
decide that uh we might consider asking
friends that already went to Hawaii or
read subreddits uh related to that. And
then this this uh framework introduce a
mechanism for getting a score for each
of these actions. Um and then kind of
update the search space or the
trajectory of follow-up kind of
expansion of this tree that is being
formed based on that score. So in this
case and we talked about how these
scores are generated in this case action
one has a higher score. So we expand
that action. So the model expands that
action. Um so in this case ask two
friends uh about uh friend A and friend
B about opinions and then based on the
quality of responses there's score for
that and we can follow on from from uh
the model can expand from there. So
there is a there's a flavor of
multi-action sampling. In this case, the
actions can be in fact ex be executed in
parallel like these two actions or these
two actions. They both can be executed
in parallel. And there's this notion of
like let's do continue exploration based
on the best state but also consider
a a mix of exploration and exploitation.
And that's where the MCTS comes in.
Um so there are two kind of papers that
uh this paper was basically saying how
it diverges from those. Math sheepard is
a paper that we saw previously and in
that paper there was a verifier that was
guiding the search process uh in the
test time. Basically um the the
reasoning kind of trajectories are
scored by this verifier and then um the
the the expansion is uh guided by that.
But in lats which is this paper that we
are going to uh learn more about in this
lecture uh the scoring is not based on
reasoning choices but it's based on the
outcomes of the actions that the model
takes. uh and also there is this part
about reflection of the model to kind of
evaluate how this trajectory went uh and
um also about the observations from the
environment. Um it also improves based
on previous uh methods uh uh frameworks
and reasoning such as the React work. um
where um basically in React uh
there there is this extra step of we're
going to see how this works but there is
this extra step of kind of memorization
and again reflection and then
interaction with the environment that we
have in the lats uh p paper and
specifically we have more and more
planning in into the process
So um here is uh the intuition
[clears throat] uh behind lats. Uh there
is the chain of thought uh where the
reasoning process is basically
decomposed into a number of steps. There
is this notion of tree expansion. Um
basically through this type types of
actionings that action uh generation
that we have we have a tree that we form
a tree and we do search and planning
through that and then we have this kind
of like borrowed that from the react
framework where uh the feedback from
these actions are incorporated into into
this search process for the future
search search and so on.
So this method concretely has six types
of kind of uh
uh stages.
Selection, expansion, evaluation,
simulation, back propagation and
reflection. So let's see exactly how
this method works. Um and let's walk
through an example an example prompt. So
in this case, the prompt is um navigate
through a maze to reach an exit. Um and
then the initial observation is that
you're in a dimly lit room. There are
two doors, one on the left and one on
the right. And the goal is to reach an
exit in this case. So let's see how
these different steps of lats uh come
into play. So first is the selection
process. In this stage, we need to
select a node to expand. Let's say we
have done that. We see exactly how
that's done. Uh but given a node, we
want to see what kind of actions we can
given that we have selected a node and
this is based on UTC. We're going to see
it in a bit. We want to see what kind of
actions that we can take from that node.
So in this case our initialized node is
uh this thing you're in a dimly lit room
and so on. Now let's say the model
samples different actions here. In this
case three actions are sampled. One is
open the left door, open the right door
and the third one is inspect the room
for clues. Then the next step is each of
these actions are executed in the
environment and the observation is kind
of basically appended to uh to the
context. So in this case say if the
action is open the left room the
observation is dark corridor with
paintings. Action B is open the right
there's another observation and so on
for action C.
Now uh comes the evaluation. So let's
say we have an action. We have executed
an action. We want to evaluate our new
state that we are going into. For this
part um they suggest averaging for
creating a score based on the current uh
kind of action and observation. They
suggest adding up two scores together.
One is using an LM score basically
prompting using LLM as a judge and
prompting the model for the for
evaluating how promising this state is
and literally asking it to give a score
based on 0 to one for this state and the
other one is the self-consistency score
and that is let's assume instead of
three actions here we had sampled
uh 50 times
um we had sampled called 50 actions and
we categorize them into different types
of actions. And if an action is sampled
more, we kind of give a score like we
give a score corresponding to the the
rate or the frequency of an action being
sampled. So in this case, the
self-consistency
score for state A was higher because 75%
of the time maybe the action A was um uh
sampled. So the way to create just one
value for this state for this action is
to add up these two. So now we have a
value for for action A corresponding to
to to state SA.
Um and then we have the simulation part.
For example in a greedy method we from
the previous stage we have SA having the
highest score. SB and S SC have much
lower scores. So we we go and expand SA
all the way again we can continue this
process we sample more uh from SA and we
continue expansions until we reach an
end state or or whether it's successful
or it fails or until we reach a a maxim
the budget that we have for expansion of
this state. So um in this case from
state SA um so this was SA and then we
have um the candidate actions that start
from that state and then in this case
it's greedy it takes one approach one
action approach the staircase um and
then we reach an observation
uh which we are lucky in this case we
have the exit door clearly marked we we
got a point here.
Um and then let's say the simulation is
done. We either have an successful
trajectory or it's a failure. Um uh then
we can we the important part here is how
do we use this observation to kind of
backrop and update the scores that we
had for different actions that were
taken. So this is the backrop stage and
then that is used to influence the score
of each each state um and uh and we're
going to talk about it in a bit. Okay,
let's talk about how these value
function and back propagation is used.
So for the value function we already saw
that that is a weighted average of
asking an LLM as a judge given this
observation this action how do you have
what are the chances of success give us
a score between 0 to one and then
there's the self-consistency which
basically we just count how many times a
given action is sample
then there is the notion of UCT or upper
confidence bounds applied to trees
that's something that this is the the
the basically the number or score that
is used for selection because we have at
each point we have a range of like
values that we want to see which node we
go and expand. So the way UCT works and
this is like completely borrowed from
the MCTS kind of literature. Uh
the way it's designed is to try to
balance between exploration and
exploitation. If we just go based on the
highest value at that point, we might
miss out other nodes that right now
maybe at the current moment have a lower
uh value but down the road at the end
might have higher value. So let's
balance the the two of them. So the way
UCT works is that it has this
exploitation
uh one which is V of S plus a
hyperparameter times this other term
which encourages exploration. And the
way this work here is that the np is the
parent the number of times a parent of a
node is visited and ns is the number of
the nodes that this current node is not
the parent but the current node is
visited. And basically think about it
this way relative to the parent node. If
a node is visited less we want to
encourage visiting that node more. And
if that node relative to the parent is
in is visited um a high a large number
of times then this number this uh
division this becomes a smaller number
and UCT becomes
uh lower relative to unexplored kind of
children of a parent node. So um UCT
again is the number that we use for
expans for selection of a node and going
from there. Now back propagation and
that's where we go at the end of an a
trajectory either we succeed or fail the
return of that trajectory is used to
update the values and this is like back
propagated through the the steps. So at
each point the value of an of a state is
the value of the old state times the
number of v visits to that to that node
uh minus one plus the return divided by
the total number of visits to that node.
So that's that's how the math behind
this um framework. Yes.
UCP
one
long
take a long
>> it's it's just something there's some
math and theoretical intuitions behind
it. There's no proof that this is the
optimal round but you want to just
balance the two in that like this is
considered a more optimized way of doing
things. Oh.
>> Yes. Yes. Um
so once back propagation is done uh they
also they also append this reflection of
the model itself about the uh the
trajectory that was expanded. If it
fails or if it succeeds, the model adds
some thinking behind what happened, what
led to the failure or the success of
this trajectory. And this apparently has
been very helpful in overall increasing
the quality of this approach.
Um so they tested this approach on
hotspot QA which is some data set that
we still uh uh we use it for multi-step
reasoning optimization. Basically the
way this data set works is that for each
question for answering them you need
retrieval from at least two like
different Wikipedia pages um because
it's just designed like that. So you
need this multi-step by design kind of
process in order to find an answer and
um obvious and they're doing really well
like just look in in terms of like as
they increase the number of samples or
the number of trajectories that they
sample they can significantly improve
performance.
um and the the the reflection and
bringing those kind of reasoning traces
also gives a lot of boosts at the end to
the model. So basically they have
provided a mechanism to um translate
more compute at test time effectively to
better kind of uh solutions for this
multi-step reasoning tasks. Um they also
tested that on webshaw which is this
interesting um data set uh for practical
app applications.
Um
there are um this is like just to show
you an example how this data set works.
For example, there is I'm looking for a
small portable hoarding desk that's
already fully assembled. It should have
a this color and this finish and so on
and the prices. So it's by design it's a
very multi-step pro it's a multi-step
process and um they're showing that
their approach without any kind of
fine-tuning and just at test time they
can get really high results even close
to human um experts in this case. Uh
so to summarize what LZ proposed was a
new technique for kind of bringing in
reasoning uh taking actions and planning
all together and kind of brought in our
known ideas like MCTS into the into the
language model world. um and they got
very strong results on multiple domains
and um given the test time approach and
the modular approach it's very portable
and easy to uh relatively easy to
create. The downside of course is the
cost. um
um each of these kind of like back
propagation and like expansion of a tree
all of those are adding a lot of cost
and um they like um the cost benefits
was not really analyzed in the paper.
Another assumption that this is not this
paper didn't address was really that um
there are scenarios where taking an
action may be reversible. So there are
that's going to be challenging like how
do we adapt uh to those scenarios right
if like for example the model is running
a transaction like if if it actually
takes those actions it could be very
consequential like paying for a service
and so on. So so that is another uh
scenario where u this approach might not
be um adaptable to. So here there are a
few questions about this paper that I
really would like you to think about it
maybe for a couple minutes and then we
discuss uh anything related to where you
see the strengths or weaknesses of this
paper or if you were to adapt it or
extend it how do you how would you do
that?
So let's start doing that and I'll get
back to you in a couple of minutes.
All right, let's get back. Anyone wants
to comment on on this fork?
>> So the UCT method, it's basically like
confidence found like from like bandit
learning setting, right? There's other
algorithms for like picking like in
bandit learning like picking and
exploring various arms. Did they try
like different ones in this paper?
>> Okay, the question you think is one way
to create this exploration.
There are a lot of literature. know that
whether they compared.
>> Yeah.
>> Um no and there is that whole literature
multi-arm bandit and other ways that we
can uh bring in exploration exploitation
into the optimization process and all of
that could be like also explored here.
They just like I think their main
contribution is that created a platform
that now can others can bring in other
approaches to optimization.
Yeah. Anything else?
Questions or comments?
Okay, let's move on to the next paper.
>> Yes, go ahead. Um so if we were to keep
track of um the action trajectory based
with the Monte Carlo tree search what if
there were times when there's like
repeated actions like action A B A B if
or or like um when the same action is
seen in multiple nodes uh is there any
way to optimize this tree or does this
tree recognize all of these repeated
actions as uh independent trajectories?
Um so the question is if if a series of
actions are repeated how do you so so
the whole the philosophy behind this is
that if an action is repeated in inside
a trajectory
um given a parent node you would count
you would increase the count of that
action and that comes in in the UCT
formulation right so to ideally you
would capture that in that as you are
forming this tree and ideally this is a
tree that you're forming not like some
kind of like fully connected graph. So
this is kind of the assumption behind
behind this. Yes.
So let's uh now talk about spring. This
is a new 2025 paper. So this hasn't been
even presented here at the conference.
Uh uh so the the this paper is about
again it gives you a flavor of um this
kind of like planning and parallel
execution of those plans and how we can
kind of use the model itself to enable
it to think better in parallel and uh we
can opt and optimize that. So the paper
this paper sprint was motivated by this
observation that the reasoning models
such as 01 Gemini think Gemini 2.5 Pro
and um pretty much all the frontier
models right now they um they have this
tendency that for harder problems they
think more and this long longer thinking
corresponds to higher accuracy. So we
kind of like these models to think for
longer and longer kind of like chain of
thoughts. Uh for example, these two
graphs here show that the deepseek R1
during the training process as the
training process continues uh obviously
it becomes better at solving this ammy
these math problems but also if we take
a look at the average length per
response that is also going up. So it
seems like there is a correlation
between model thinking for longer and a
larger sum of to number of tokens and
the accuracy that we get from that.
Now um again so the observation here was
that many uh like these long reasoning
steps are helpful but at the same time
many of these reasoning steps seem to be
independent of each other. Um
for example the model tries alternative
approaches. It deco composes a task into
subtasks that some of them can be run in
parallel. Um and then some of these
steps are verifying the previous steps.
So but there is a lot of if you look
into the graph that describes a uh kind
of the reasoning trace um there are
parts of these computations that are
independent of of each other. So we
don't need to really wait for all of
these steps to be to be kind of created
sequentially by the model. So we want to
see how we can leverage this parallelism
observation. And uh so the idea is we
want the model identify this
parallelization opportunities and kind
of act on it. So sprint sprint is a
framework that um does come in during
the post- training and or fine-tuning
process and what it does is that it
takes a reasoning model and enables the
reasoning model to execute the uh like
the response generation via a um planner
and a planner that creates a set of
plans for how to approach solving a
problem and a set of executors
and those executors can be run in
parallel in order to ex like carry out
the plan and this can happen again and
again. We can have the next one we can
have a plan a bunch of um kind of uh
execution plans that are carried out in
parallel and then we can have another
set of plans and then another set of
parallel uh executions. uh so this inter
uh the interleing of this planning and
execution is what it can enable
acceleration of the reasoning process.
So let's say how we can enable that how
we can enable the model to create these
parallel kind of traces.
Um and this is a this is something that
I want you to kind of think about it
beyond just this paper and you're seeing
it in the following work that we are
talking about. uh a lot of times when we
want to show to kind of uh create data
and figure out a certain behavior in the
model we can use the LLMs itself in in
the syn like the fine-tuning data
creation process and here is an example
of that of that given a reasoning model
uh models response trajectory to a
question to a qu to a question we can
decompose it in the number of steps we
and LLM. So in this case for example we
had D6 R1 generate these reasoning
traces and responses to these questions
and then we had a model like GPT40 going
through this reasoning trace and create
this annotate the steps of the reasoning
the reasoning response and not only that
for each of these steps we ask the GPT40
to annotate whether this is which part
is the planning part and which part is
the execution part and in some steps
there were multiple execution pieces for
a given plan.
Um so for example we had this query we
had the reasoning traits and then there
are a bunch of things that needs to be
done and then when the reasoning uh
stops there's a final answer answer then
we use GPT40 to go through this process
and kind of like create these steps one
2 and k basically now we have these
annotations and within each step the
model also uh kind of annotates the plan
and the execution. Which part is the
planning part? Which part is the
execution of that plan?
Given that then we can create a DAG of
these uh steps. So we have step one,
step two and all the way. And we can
again use the model and the model does a
really good job here of saying whether
how these steps are related to each
other. For example, step four and two
are not dependent on each other, but
they both depend on step one is a
follow-up to a step one. So now we have
like a DAG of um an optimiz and
basically creating a DAG that um
describes how this reasoning trace
works. Um and then we can do packing of
these steps. For example, step one can
be done first and step two and three can
be done completely in parallel with each
other and so on. Um and
once we have these data set um that we
have annotated then LRM here is just a
large reasoning model. Basically all uh
LLMs are now inherently reasoning
models. So what we are uh creating here
is this data set of the steps plan and
executions in parallel and we basically
fine-tune the model the for example deep
R1 to now think in that way. So
previously would just create those um
inherently have these properties but now
we want the model to think more and more
in parallel by showing these parallel
like planning and execution traces and
we just fine-tune the model in this case
just the supervised finetuning of
basically showing the model the same the
same stuff the same thinking processes
but now annotated with these tags
um
And this helps the model that at
inference time now the model can out uh
can output these tags. For example, here
is plan one and then here are the
execution um patterns for this and here
is plan two and so on. So for example
for pan I there is a set of thinking and
the parallel execution that the model
just outputs itself and then we can uh
kind of go over executing these plans in
parallel and then syncing the output and
returning the context and then the model
goes through plan I + 1 and then there's
a part of there's a number of parallel
um kind of sub plans within that that
the model can uh uh output and we can go
from there.
Uh why this matters? Um
so the cost of LLM inference especially
when we get to multi-step reasoning
becomes a huge burden. Um and you might
have already noticed that yourself when
you spend a lot of time waiting for the
model to output a response. It gets
um it might get uh it might make you
kind of like not happy. you want the
answers fast but also it's a lot of cost
and a lot of delay that goes into
generating these responses. So right now
here is how the sequential reasoning
models work. So there's a query, there's
a plan and then execution of that plan.
There's plan two, execution of plan two
and so on. So this is the time that it
takes to generate or like go over this
thinking process and generate a final
answer. But if we could kind of leverage
this independence from um plan one and
plan two, we could have the model
um execute we could have the execution
of those plans be done um at the same
time. Here is what after we fine-tune
with the spring at inference time
happens. So instead of model generating
plan one and executing that then
generating plan two, model generates
these two plans first plan one and two
and then and then and then it starts
executing the execution of those plans
happen at the same time and then the
execution could be using a tool. For
example, the model is come up with a
calculation and then we can use this
calculator or Python to execute plan one
and plan two and so on and then go to
the next step next stage and the
fine-tuning data. Again, this is another
visualization of how given these
annotations that we have for plans and
execution, we create the fine-tuning
data. So we are basically asking the
model to think in parallel if the plans
are independent of each other. We are
basically teaching the model to come up
with plan one and two at the same time
because they're independent of each
other and we execute them. Yes.
>> So if there's a need for ref planning,
how does the model remember which plans
corresponding to which executions and
like all of those things, right? Like at
like later in the stage, right? Like if
like after the execution of four
>> the one who realizes that oh what I did
was wrong. How does it remember to like
do a refining of like go to the plan of
three instead of like two you know
>> uh how
so this this work I I think you are kind
of like bringing the previous work in
here like here the model can so what we
are teaching the model here is that to
think about plans at each point of time
even if it's a like a revision of an
existing plan if it can generate plans.
If it if it can generate plans that can
be uh executed in parallel, it should do
so. It should not wait for the execution
of plan one to generate plan two because
plan two has is independent of plan one
anyway. Right? So this is how we are
creating this data set for training the
model to teaching it to think maximally
in parallel and generate those plans. If
the model wants to go back and reverse
on a plan, it still can do that. It
still sees all of these kind of context.
It's just like the model is trained to
think more in parallel and also because
it's trained to be like that. And we
have these special kind of tags or ways
of the model generating these plans and
execution plans we can act on it and
enable leverage those parallelism.
Yes.
actually change the structure of this
outline because before you just need to
predict the next token but now you see
you have three parallel uh lines
>> it's always next token it's just that
there is like instead of like everything
the plan and execution one at a time if
there's a tag like here this is plan I
and here are the the execution and here
is plan two plan I and I + one for
example here's plan one and PL plus two.
This is the high level count. And then
now that we know that there are these
two plans, we can just grandchild and
run them in parallel. So that's that's
the idea here. Um
so here is the training recipe starting
from so we generate 6K thinking
trajectories for math data set. um
we keep the ones with higher
parallelization
and we do supervised fine-tuning on um
deepse R1 distill 7B on this reformatted
trajectories and the interesting
property that we observed was that uh so
when we started the project the goal was
to maximize parallelism for reducing the
the sequential
token generation. So we save on that.
But it turns out this process actually
helps out with accuracy as well. Like
the model seems to like this kind of
more structured way of thinking and this
uh way of encouraging parallelism helps
the model have higher accuracy as well.
And here what we are showing that is the
average number of sequence sequential
tokens over the baseline model like R1
distill 7B and this the sprint model
again is distilling R1 this basically
there we are fine-tuning the 7B model
and there's a big jump like a 3 and a
half% jump over that um while also
becoming more much more efficient than a
32B model in terms of um number of
sequential tokens
>> might increase by more authentics for
more approaches given the fixed computer
because it
>> it could be yeah there is and we have
some data on that which I believe I'm
going to show yeah the model does
explore more and think in parallel
more and the another interesting
observation was that um
we have out of domain generalization as
well. So the thinking to train to like
sorry training to think in parallel was
done for the math data set but we also
saw the model is doing better not only
have lower have more opportunities for
this parallelism but also higher
accuracy for um for example uh countdown
or GPQA diamond data set. So there is no
training like we have not trained on
those data set but the model generalizes
and this like could go back to what
you're suggesting that the model can
think in parallel and that inherently
seems to help the model but at a as a
side effect um we also have
opportunities for leveraging this
parallelism parallelism and reducing the
number of sequential tokens. Could there
be a scenario where [clears throat]
individually uh the answers are correct
in the final uh you know in the parallel
branches but when you combine it say in
a sequential manner the answer may be
wrong and in that case what will take
precedence
>> and in that case what
>> what will take precedence because
sometimes given in a mathematical
equation individually when you look at
them in isolation the answer might look
seemingly correct but when you put them
and put all the steps together the
answer will be eventually.
>> Yeah. So, so when we when the model
generates the no matter if it generates
sequentially or in parallel there at the
end of the day everything is condensed
into the context. So the model sees that
and this is the thinking process. The
answer after this the model should
generate a synthesize a final answer. So
if there are con contradictions in the
sequential or in parallel the model is
expected to resolve that before
generating a final answer. So in that
case it's it's a little difficult to say
because both both approaches can be uh
can can suffer from kind of
contradictions in the thinking. But here
we are what we are seeing is more that a
like these plans are kind of like
they're rather than being different
approaches to solve the same problem
they're like different steps to to solve
uh one problem. Um so uh parallel the
another interesting observation was that
um
and perhaps intuitive some that harder
problems require more uh iterative
planning and execution. Uh the other
observation this was like maybe less
intuitive was that in the early stages
like so we have a bunch of these
parallel planning execution parallel
planning execution in the early stages
the parallelism
more parallelism or more exploration is
observed by the model and then in the
later stages uh we kind of converge to
maybe uh to to um less plans Um
yeah basically the exploration is is
more in the early stages and towards the
end we want to like really go dive deep
into a single plan and execution. Yes.
>> Um how can you ensure that the
independent reasoning tasks um are
evenly load balanced uh and do not
encounter bottlenecks like do
independent tasks for example like have
similar expected execution times? Like
here you're saying that how do we make
sure
>> right so so when we divide independent
um tasks how do we ensure that these are
going to be executed about similar
times.
>> So uh so the question is how do we
ensure that these independent plans that
are now run at the same time they're
they're uh they they have they take
similar times. But the thing is we can
is we can ensure that right we we have
uh there are some kind of measures taken
to enable that but we still could have a
straggler like maybe step two versus
four here step four may take a lot
longer than step two but at the same
time we are kind of confined to just
step four not step four plus step two
runtime. Um and we have some some
measures. For example, if the the plan
um if the execution is just too simple,
we kind of merge that into the plan and
try to create these bigger and bigger
chunks that we can we can do in
parallel. But that could be an
optimization as well. The the optim
optimizing this across the stages
analysis for reasoning function.
>> I'm not sure. I'm not sure if there
analysis exactly on that. Um question.
>> Yes. Could you go back to the slide? So
uh I saw on the math and GDPA the uh
spring it has comparable accuracy and
number of tokens as the baseline R. So
I'm curious like for those uh benchmarks
what is the main uh width of the tree
and what's the maximum width?
>> Um
>> in terms of like cuz the width of the
tree like determines how much
parallelism you can exploit.
So you're get what you're getting at is
that with the it's task dependent
basically [clears throat] the
parallelism that we can exploit and for
some of these if the if we can the
basically if the ratio of the sequential
tokens is uh like for one task like for
example I believe for math it's like
lower than for GPQ do domain um then yes
that's an indication of parallelism like
some task could be inherently more
parallel than the
And I don't know the exact number of the
width of the tree here but that to to be
able to leverage this approach uh
parallelism should exist and it's but
but what we observed is that that is the
case for many of the reasoning problems
like math and other kind of reasoning
tasking GPQA and so on. Um and some of
these are um
again like for example if you look at
this uh for the math data set uh
compared to um
some of these methods with like even
lower but like comparable accuracy we
increasing the uh the bandwidth or um
then reducing the number of sequent
token by something like 40% which is
like a long large number Um
but um it is true that this is going to
be task dependent.
Um and maybe getting back to your
questions um we have larger savings for
problems that need more thinking. So uh
for example here we are showing the
sequential token reduction by spring
over the baseline just sorry over the uh
RFD model. This is the rejection
fine-tuning methods. So this is another
baseline that uh this is a baseline we
are comparing with. If the num the the
number of tokens in generated like in
the thinking process is small then there
is probably less opportunity for
parallelism right so by doing this like
oh let's plan and execute we are
actually we can be worse than the
baseline but this appears in the harder
problems and problems that require more
thinking and more number of parallel
tokens and that's where this method
shines and shows parallelism. Um, I'm
not sure how how many of you have read
the recent uh sonnet 4.5
system card, but it was very interesting
to me that it says the prompt for for
the system card um encourages the model
to use tools as much as possible and at
least 100 times. That's a very large
number that we the model is encouraged
to use the tool. And this is like just
shows that for we are going into this
regime that we are solving more and more
interesting problems and we are actually
go going more and way beyond 8 to 10k
even for the number of tokens that the
model deals with for solving a problem.
Um yes
data set diagram on all your
>> uh fine chain process
uh I think one
>> yeah doing inference does it um produce
the entire um like step one to step k
the entire thing but different layers or
does it do a sequential
>> no during inference um it kind just like
this. So the model learns to generate
plans that can be executed in parallel
at the same time. So it first generates
plan one and two, plan one and two and
then once plan one um like is outputed
execution of plan one starts. One plan
once plan two is outputed execution of
plan two starts then the result is uh
put back in the context and then the
model is generating two two more plans.
So the model still takes this sequential
approach to generating plans and
execution but with the difference is
that if it kind of learns or is trained
to at each point of time if there are
plans that are can be gener can be
executed in parallel it generates those
at the same time. So here would be
generates uh after step one it generates
step two and four at the same time and
then you see the results for that and
then and then so on and it continues.
So each step, think about it, each step
is a plan and a set of executions in the
training.
>> But the step here is defined as plan one
and except one. And then it it kind of
we changed the notion of
um
>> do they also match this um like uh so so
let's say they execute two plan that
like um that can be paralyzed and then
they collect the context and then add it
to the prompt for the next uh level. So
they also do that in the training phase
as well to match like how they are
prompting it. The training is shown
here. This is how the training data will
look like.
>> So plan one and two are independent. So
plan one and two are put together like
next to each other. And then we have
execution one and two during training.
So that's how the model sees
um during training that platum one and
two could could be outputed together.
But at inference the execution is
actually also done in parallel.
Okay, let's move on to the last paper
because I want to make sure we cover
that. But just before that opportunity,
so here the the work that supervised
fine-tuning, but of course methods like
RL and GRPO can enable potentially much
more kind of benefit from this data and
much more kind of this generalization
property usually works well with RL. um
um and and other other kind of notions
about tool use overlapping different
tools or like doing um actually
realizing the wall clock speedups is
other work that can be done here in the
implementation of this method. Um so now
let's go through another method called
swirl. This is also a kind of
continuation of multi-step
synthetic data generation and
encouraging the model to do to and
helping the model do multi-step better.
And this is a work that is going to be
presented next week at column um in
conference and language modeling in
Montreal. So this is another just a
preview. This is another training like
you're using training and basically
fine-tuning a language model to help it
do multi-step reasoning better. So
motivation again many real world tasks
require multi-step reasoning and tool
use. For example, if you want to answer
a multihop question using a search
engine, you want to solve math problems
or use solving a software engineering
like doing a project, planning a trip,
analyzing data and so on. Usually we go
as humans we use these tools and reason
through them for like uh important task
more than once. So we need a cohesive
kind of number of steps of reasoning and
tool use in order to solve a uh problem.
So the challenges again in multi-step
reasoning and tool use setting is that
um
when you're doing reasoning and tool use
even for one step it can get complicated
but as we expand on this and generate
multiple steps of reasoning and tool use
the errors and the complications can
compound over these different steps. Um
if we want the model to and the another
focus of this paper is enabling tool use
like teaching the model to write to use
the right tools for example a calculator
Python executor and so on. Using these
tools live during the training process
can be very challenging because tools
can fail they can be slow and the
training process is already kind of like
time consuming and challenging. So this
can further slow that down. Um
and if you look back in terms of like
the fine-tuning processes such as
reinforcement learning from human
feedback from AI feedback or execution
feedback many of these are optimized on
the singlestep kind of are optimized for
singlestep task. Basically the model
takes a lot of whatever it wants to do
generates a final answer and the reward
is just based on the final answer
whether it's correct or not and then we
kind of back propagate that towards a
actions and here we want to have a more
have a have more kind of governance and
kind of uh
uh on the process of generating these
steps and how we can optimize them. Uh
so this framework called swirl um
and the design goal for SAR is the
following. First of all
at a high level we want the model to
solve complex uh problem and multi-step
reasoning task. Um we want the model to
know when to call a tool. Um generate
the right queries to invoke a tool
because we need to know how to use a
tool like the model needs to know that.
um carry out these reasoning steps and
maintain accuracy across them um and
learn to how to recover from error and
learn to when to stop taking new steps
and calling new tools and be and say
okay I'm now ready to generate a final
answer. So we want the model to know
these steps. We also uh want to avoid
using tools during the training process
uh because like I mentioned this can be
slow tools can fail and we we and can
have bugs. We want to avoid that and
ideally we want the model to generalize
this. So ideally we want the model to
learn how to you when to adapt to new
tools and new reasoning uh tasks and
capabilities.
So to approach this the um here's the
here's the process. The first step of
this process is that let's start with
creating synthetic
let's start with creating synthetic
multi-step data for a model. So given a
prompt um and in order to really like
annotate these steps, let's have the
model um take one step at a time and
let the model know at each step that is
free to reason, create a chain of
thought, call a tool, um or propose a
final answer. So having an input prompt
at step one, we tell the model, you have
access to these tools. Uh you can
generate a reasoning step. If you're
ready to to generate the final answer,
just say that and create that. U so
given this prompt, the model can would
take the first action which could be a
reasoning step followed by the by a tool
call and then we show the model the
environment response.
Um
so given that then we ask the model
again we show the model again the same
prompt but this time we have kind of the
context from the previous step. So
basically we say here is the original
prompt here is the previous action and
here is the result of taking that action
from the environment. You can take a new
action which is and call the tool or if
you're ready to create the final answer
just uh output the final answer. So by
design we are this through through this
adapt to iterative prompting we are
creating this multi-step data set and
the steps can be from one to three or
five and so on for different queries.
um
the then we need kind of a label. We
want to to um have an a notation of how
good this uh step is. And to do to do
so, we can we ask an LLM as a judge
given the prior context and the current
action which is a reasoning state
followed by a tool call give us a reward
function. give us like your estimate of
how good this uh kind of trajectory and
final action is.
Um given that we have for each query and
reason we have a set of steps and for
each step we have a LLM as a judge kind
of like score that is assigned to that
step and we can do that offline. We can
go through many many questions in
parallel offline and generate these
steps and uh labeled annotations.
Once we have these uh steps per prompt,
we can filter this data in different
ways. For example, um we can only keep
the data where the the judge LLM as a
judge kind of decided every single step
was a good kind of step. Every single
action was good. Or we can go based on
outcome filter data and that would be we
just keep we keep all the trajectories
that the final answer was correct no
matter what the label per step was. And
we're going to see how these two kind of
deferred with each other. But the whole
part the whole pro the whole kind of
like intuition motivation behind this
part is that for for these reasoning pro
prompts we have a number of pre like a
number of steps and then for each step
we have a reward uh created by the model
which we can use or not use during our
training. But let's see how these two
play out. Um then having this data that
we have generated offline we can start
the training process and this training
in this part is done based on
reinforcement learning. So maybe you can
pay attention to this figure on the
right. Um this is a very simple example
but let's go through that. Who is older?
Glenn who I don't know the last name or
Rossling. So these two people who is
older. So action one is to figure out
who is older. I should first search for
age of the first person.
Then we have a reward for this action.
We ask the judge LLM as a judge to say
given an input prompt and this action
what is the reward for this uh step.
Then we have the then we actually go and
um
show the model um the result of this
step. This is already we have in our
training data. So we have the
environment resp response and then we
prompt the model to to take the next
action and in the next action is the
second question which is about the age
of the second person. We have a reward
based on that and at the last stage we
say given the result of the previous
searches we we ask the model to generate
the final another action. In this case
the model seems to be ready to to output
the final answer. So it outputs the
answer in these tags answer and u and uh
uh the final answer is there and we can
get a reward based on that. Uh so the
point that I want you to pay attention
to is how we manage to not have the tool
calls during training. So basically what
we are doing here is that we have this
trajectory from the prompt and from
these um kind of uh pre pre-esign pre
kind of collected actions and tool calls
during RL process we get the reward we
show the the prompt and steps and
actions onto that action K in this case
for example up to action one and the
environment response
And then that we ask the model to take
the next step. So this is the part that
is done during training. The the model
takes the next action but before but we
don't need to execute that action or
call the tool. We just collect a reward
based on that um specific action um and
use that for RL optimization. All the
tool calls are just done during the data
annotation process outside of the RL
fine-tuning part. Um because we realize
that the model the the LLMs just does a
good job based on the quality of the
action that's proposed. We're good on
just evaluating that. We don't need to
get execute the action and evaluate
that. So that's how we separated the
two.
We so we did not need we did not train
an LLM as a judge for this. We just
prompted uh I I'll talk about what
models we used for each one.
So there was no training for that.
>> But if you if the judge cannot see the
real like
from
how can like judge
>> Yeah. So the jud So the question is if
the judge cannot see the output of the
tool how can it give a reasonable score.
So the here's the the point here. So we
are asking the judge to judge the
quality of the the query that is
generated by the model to call the tool
rather than the output of the tool. Like
here what the judge sees is that the
model is asking age of this person right
and the model can judge that this is a
good kind of question to create for the
search engine
it before seeing the result of the
search engine right the model doesn't
need to know the age of this person to
know this question was good or bad this
is a good question this is a reasonable
question right
Um
so basically what we are doing is
providing this process feedback process
reward for this step and the tool calls
are captured in the prior context. So
all of these tool call resources is we
have collected them in our offline
training data set. We are not doing that
during during the actual RL fine-tuning.
So um to just show you the objective
function that we that is being optimized
in this multi-step RL is
let's say we have a number of steps S S1
to SK and then each followed by an
action which is a reasoning step
followed by a tool call. What we are
doing here is that we are optimizing the
expected reward of an action of a single
action given all the context so far
which is a set of states and actions
that we have collected off.
Um so that's [snorts] how we are
optimizing the expected reward of an
action of a single action in a
multi-step process given all the prior
steps. But of course this action this
varies from action one all the way to
action K.
Um now during inference
once we RL this model we let's walk
through an inference process of how we
encourage the model to do this
multi-step process. So for example here
the the user the prompt is help me
answer the following questions uh in
just a few words.
uh and then we uh specify the tool that
the model can use. In this case, a
calculator. If you think it would help
to use a calculator, please generate a
mathemat mathematical query uh enclosed
by this kind of these kind of tags. Um
and then
we also tell the model once you have
enough information you can generate an
answer tag and generate the final
answer. So through these tags, the model
can tell us the tool call um or or or if
it's ready to generate the final answer.
So here is the input question. Uh so in
step one, the model is prompted um here
is the input question. The model u uh
responses to that question. uh and it in
this response is calling it the
calculator and it's calling this uh kind
of like this is the math that it wants
to run. The user provides that um output
like basically that tool is executed
with that given input. We give the
output to the model and then the model
is prompted again
again here is the input here is the
result from the previous kind of like
thinking process and tool call. Um and
the model takes the next action and and
next action and so far. Um so we are
kind of iteratively prompt the model.
Here is what happened so far. Here's the
tool you have. If you're ready to
generate the final answer, do it. If
not, continue using the tool.
So the experimental setup for this
approach was the following. We have
there is a uh mod GMO 227B
used to was used to create this
multi-step synthetic data. Uh the
questions were coming from hotspot QA
and GSM8K.
uh we had something like 50k
trajectories
uh sourced from a number of problems and
created for uh different kinds of data
that were like I said we can process
this data that we created based on
process filter
outcome filtered both process and uh
outcome filtered or random and then we
also corrected a number of trajectories
I think um so let's take a look at
impact of data of filtering on the
performance of swirl. Um one perhaps in
the beginning this was non-intuitive but
we kind of realized what why this is
happening is that it seems like when our
training data was only process filtered
meaning we took reasoning steps that
were majority like uh uh voted yes by
LLM as a judge from the reasoning steps
but we kind of like didn't filter them
based on the correctness of final
answer. This seems to help the the
process more the the training more than
if we kind of rigorously
uh only took trajectories where the
outcome was uh correct or both process
and outcome were correct. Um, and the
reason for that is if we only get
trajectories where the model already
knows the outcome and is correct,
perhaps you're not helping the model
solve problems that it couldn't solve
during test time because you're training
it to think differently about these
problems. So, it can solve new problems
that it couldn't solve before, but it
had kind of gotten the some processes uh
correctly.
Um but perhaps the most interesting and
this is again something that we are
seeing in the sprint project as well is
the generalization performance of the
model. So for example we had a swirl on
GSM8K. These are math problems and we
were teaching the model to use like simp
calculator basically to solve these
problems. Uh so that was the training
data and then we when once we kind of
did do this multi-step RL optimization
using GSM8K we then tested on hotspot QA
and this is the accuracy that uh
increase that we get from the base
model. So it goes from 65 to 751.
And if we were to use exactly hotspot QA
and in this case the tool for hotspot QA
was a search tool uh not a calculator
the optimization the increase was from
65 to 73. So and vice versa this was
true as well. If we train the model on
hotspot QA with a search tool it could
also do well on GSM8K with Python. So it
seems like there is something going
beyond just like learning to use a
specific tool. Rather the model is
learning how to think in steps and how
learn how to invoke a tool. Um and and
this was perhaps u and and these data
sets the other data sets are separate uh
from uh any of our training data.
Uh another uh important observation here
was that again in this case we were the
model is being trained on hotspot QA
using a search tool for all of these but
we are showing the test results um as we
are increasing this synthetic data the
training data size. So it seems like as
we go from 100 training examples to uh
10,000 training examples even at
inference the model is improving on a
completely different task which is math
problems and GSM8K.
So this is like again u I think it's the
most important graph from this paper
showing that by creating synthetic data
in environments that are perhaps like
easier to create create these data for
and teaching the model how to use these
tools and how to do think uh in multi
multiple steps. We can generalize these
behavior to entirely new tools and
domains. And perhaps scaling this up
could be a very um kind of imp powerful
uh methodology.
Um
and here we are showing some results on
the like to to kind of try to interpret
why the model is becoming better uh by
in through this RL processes. And what
we did here is to look into the average
kind of process reward per step of the
model in answering these questions
before and after being fine-tuned uh
through this reinforcement learning
process. And perhaps this is again very
intuitive that the process correctness
of the model has improved throughout
this process for both in distribution
domain where we train on hotspot QA and
out of dist out of distribution when we
just tested on GSM8K. So the model
thinks more correctly per step both for
on the training data but on other but
out of distribution data. And here are
some other results um that uh we can
also be look also looked into precision,
recall and other metrics across a number
of tasks. Um
um and um here are how this works
compared to frontier models. Um
something that is uh perhaps it's worth
noting here is that
we could do all of this that all of this
process that we did with RL we could do
it with supervised finetuning as well
and it turns out that this multi-step RL
does better by a good amount over
supervised finetuning
uh and especially for supervised
finetuning it seemed like the model
really benefited like the training data
needed to be correct like both process
and outcome filtered um supervised
finding on that kind of training data
worked better than when we only uh when
we selected only the process filtered
data and it kind of makes sense because
in supervised fine-tuning we're kind of
it's kind of an imit imitation learning
right we're showing these are the
trajectories and we want the model to
repeat those in a Okay. Uh whereas in
the and then if they're incorrect, the
outcome is incorrect. It might hurt
performance. Whereas in RL, we are
giving the model a new chance in in to
take a new action given the prior steps
and we are kind of giving a reward based
on that new action and that's how it can
break out from this. Um and here are
some other results. Um but because we're
out of time let's just take a look at
the summary of this. Uh so again a
important observation was that sort
generalizes across data sets and tools.
um it transfers to desperate task. H and
the model learns better from process
filtered data and it can get get a lot
of gains from more synthetic data both
for in domain and out of domain and um
and from an just understanding why this
happens. It turns out that after this
sort of fine-tuning the process behavior
like the process correctness of the
model improves. So if we just go to
evaluate that the model becomes better
at this multi-step um thinking um again
this is true for both in distribution
and out of distribution uh data and with
that you can conclude this lecture.
I hope you learn more about multistep
and reasoning and planning which is a
very active field that is going forward.